Guide to the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection, 1695-1955 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton collection 1695-1955 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dalton, Harry L.
80.5 linear feet Extent: approx. 11,160 Items
Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton collected art, rare books, and manuscripts, and made many contributions to art museums and libraries, most notably the Duke University Library, the Mint Museum, and the library of the University of North Carolina at Charlotte. The Dalton Collection is comprised of sub-collections acquired by Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton.
RL.00284
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a series of gifts in 1977, 1978, 1980, 1982, and 1991.
Biographical Note
Harry Lee Dalton was born in Winston, North Carolina on June 13, 1895. A graduate of Trinity College (now Duke University), he served in the U.S. Army Air Corps during World War I. Dalton had a successful career in banking and finance and served as an officer and investor in numerous companies, including American Viscose Corporation, American Credit Corporation and Wachovia Bank. His other business interests included investments in oil extraction ventures, mainly through the Ancora Corporation.
Dalton and his wife, Mary Keesler, collected art, rare books, and manuscripts, and made many contributions to art museums and libraries, most notably the Duke University Library, the Mint Museum, and the library of the University of North Carolina at Charlotte. Dalton died in Charlotte on July 26, 1990.
Collection Overview
The Dalton Collection is comprised of sub-collections acquired by Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton. Included are family papers, correspondence, diaries, account books, photographs, engravings, land grants, and military papers. The material largely encompasses the Civil War, Southern [U.S.] history, business and politics. The material ranges in date from 1695-1955.
Each sub-collection is listed in alphabetical order below. Most include their descriptions from the catalog record as well as a link to the record which will serve to state the physical location of the sub-collections. For the small number of sub-collections not yet fully cataloged, a brief description will follow as well as which Dalton Collection box the material resides in.
Related Material
Harry L. Dalton Papers, 1776-1990
Special Collections, J. Murrey Atkins Library, UNC-Charlotte
Contents of Collection
- A-B
  - Adams Family papers, 1828
    Land grant signed by John Quincy Adams for William Mason of Huntsville, AL in 1828.
  - Andrassy, Count Julius papers, 1832-circa 1873
    One 1832 letter written in Hungarian, possibly from Andrassy's father, Karoli, as well as a couple of newspaper articles that deal with the acceptance by Count Andrassy of the post of Prime Minister of Hungary, written in English in the 1870s. Items are located in Box 1 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Arnett Family papers, 1861-1865
    Two Civil War diaries chiefly concerning camp life. Contributors to diaries are: B. A. Arnett, a private in the Buck Head Guards of the Fairfield District, S.C., his brother R. C., and his sister Sue. Entries include accounts and debts contracted during the war by the Arnett brothers.
  - Austin, Benjamin W. papers, 1798-1895
    This is the autograph and signed letter collection of Benjamin W. Austin. Many of the letters and autographs were obtained through Mr. Austin’s written request, but older items appear to have come from the autograph collection of Henry Sheldon of Salisbury, Vermont. Although many items are older, most of Mr. Austin’s active collecting was done in the 1880s and 1890s. The group includes items from Congressmen, Civil War heroes, literary figures, and educators. Of special note in the collection is a 1798 message from William Henry Harrison at Fort Washington. Many of the items are accompanied by biographical clippings and several are attached to photographs. Of particular interest are the vintage photographs of Commander Gilbert C. Wittse, naval engineer William H. Shock, and statesman and educator J. L. M. Curry.
  - Balloch, William papers, 1856-1866
    Account book (1832-1851) lists transactions with local people (including relatives). Entries document the sale of farm products; the letting of fields, vehicles, and animals; and transactions with a boarder. Occasionally Ballock was paid in labor and in trade. Form 1844-1851 Balloch used part of the book as a memorandum book, recording household and personal purchases. Cash book (1856-1866) lists objects and services bought by Balloch and names the supplier. Purchases include books and newspapers, toys, and a violin as well as household supplies. Entries also document loans made, funds handled for the town of Claremont, N.H., and drugs purchased.
  - Baylor, Mary papers, 1861
    Three letters from E. R. Brown of North Mountain, Va., to Mary Baylor, concerning her slave, William, who is imprisoned in the Hagerstown (Md.) jail. Brown offers Miss Baylor his assistance in crossing Confederate lines to retrieve William before he is sold. The final letter is an angry reply to an "impertinent" message from Miss Baylor and contains a cartoon vignette of slaves fleeing to Fort Monroe, Va., while a Southern master dressed in a white suit and with a whip attempts to stop them.
  - Beatty, Reading K. papers, 1898-1906
    Chiefly personal letters written from the Philippines by John Beatty, soldier in Company A, First Tennessee Infantry, to his brother Reading K. Beatty. Topics include: Manila; the Spanish-American War; Philippines culture; John's business ventures in the Philippines; and references to Maryville College in Tennessee. Also includes a few financial papers and printed public documents such as executive orders.
  - Beauregard, Doctor [Chevalier?] papers, 1808-1822
    Sales slips and bills of Beauregard in Philadelphia, buying medicinal goods and settling acounts (1817-1819); three letters from "Good Rest" (1822), one from his overseer, Richard Newman, one from his manager, John Cotter, and a letter from young Dr. Beauregard to his father in Augusta, Ga. An undated list of the goods and slaves of his plantation in included in the collection.
  - Beauregard, [Pierre] Gustave Toutant papers, 1860-1870s
    Papers are an estimate signed by Beauregard of the funds necessary for the operations of Fort Jackson, La., during the fiscal year ending June 30, 1861 and a report of "Sherman's March" written on 1870s stationery of the New Orleans and Carrollton Railroad Company, giving mileage and dates.
  - Bingham, Lemuel papers, 1815-1816, 1832
    Lemuel Bingham's ledger is divided into two parts: an auctioneer's sales book for a Fayetteville, N.C. auctioneers' firm listing sales of groceries and sundries from January 1815 -January 1816 and a subscription book, 1832, for the CATAWBA JOURNAL (Charlotte, N.C.).
  - Bradley Family papers, 1774-1882
    Stephen Row Bradley and his son William Czar Bradley were lawyers who, as residents of Westminster, Vermont, served in the U.S. Senate and House of Representatives respectively. Later Stephen moved to Walpole, New Hampshire. Many prominent New Englanders corresponded with them about Federalist, Republican, and Democratic politics, patronage, and legal and personal matters. Stephen's son-in-law, Samuel Griswold Goodrich ("Peter Parley") was his most frequent correspondent. Other subjects of the correspondence include the Vermont militia, relations between the U.S. and Tripoli, attitudes toward the War of 1812, surveying of the northeastern boundary between the U.S. and Canada, General Lafayette's visit to Thomas Jefferson in 1824, John Quincy Adams, Henry Clay, and Andrew Jackson.
  - Bragg, Braxton papers, 1847-1876
    Predominently letters concerning military affairs. The four items collected by the Daltons were combined with other Bragg materials in 1980.
  - Brown, Jacob Jennings papers, 1814-1825
    Collection consists of two undated engravings of Brown, a letter, and a memorandum bound in pink ribbon. The letter is addressed to the Secretary of the Navy and was written in Brown's capacity as Commander. The full title of the memorandum booklet is "Memoranda of occurences and some important facts attending the Campaign on the Niagara." Brown narrates the events of the campaign. There are verified copies of major communications during the campaign, including messages from J.C. Calhoun, James Monroe, General Ripley, and others. Of special interest is a sort of appendix consisting of "An Estimate of the British Regular Troops in Upper Canada, July 1, 1814. With a view of their distribution." It is a detailed look at early nineteenth century military conflicts.
  - Buchanan, James papers, 1841-1859
    One letter dated 1841, land grants signed by Buchanan; and an 1856 pamplet entitled, The Agitation of Slavery. Who Commenced! and Who Can End It!! Buchanan and Fillmore Compared from the Record.
  - Burns, Robert, undated
    Letter from Burns to an unnamed friend in Edinburgh thanking him for the gift of a set of the writings of Edmund Spenser. Burns closed the letter with a stanza of poetry. Transcription of the letter is included.
  - Butler, Benjamin Franklin papers, 1864-1893
    Primarily letters, most to O. D. Barrett regarding financial matters. Also included are references to organized labor, the eight-hour law, and Butler's attitude toward African Americans.
  - Butler, Matthew Calbraith papers, 1851-1920
    Collection is primarily composed of Butler's personal and political correspondence. A few letters relate to his cousins in Louisiana. He sends detailed accounts of the war to his wife, Maria, daughter of S.C. Governor Pickens. Butler vividly describes battles, troop movements, and camp life. After the war, some correspondence deals with his Senate office, including his involvement in the Spanish evacuation of Cuba. Other papers concern his son's murder and legal matters. There are poems, genealogical materials, a 32-page memoir of Reconstruction in S.C. by Butler's daughter, plus an essay by her.
- C-D
  - Cist, Lewis Jacob papers, 1726-1896, undated
    283 autographed letters collected by Cist, largely of military officers as well as writers and scientists.
  - Civil War, Miscellany papers, 1860-1865
    Thirty-eight items that relate to the Civil War. Mainly correspondence, the material represents both the Union and the Confederacy. Of note is an 1862 petition signed by 74 citizens of De Soto and Marshall Counties in Mississippi in an effort to have a negro named Isaac returned to De Soto County from the protection of General Sherman. Isaac was accused of the rape and murder of a local woman, Ellen Vines. The items are located in Box 2 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Clawson, Jacob H. papers, 1820-1862
    Collection consists mostly of correspondence concerning business dealings among Clawson's family members in Berkeley County, W. Va. Although most of the items in this collection concern the collection of old debts, several letters from Thomas Dunn outline the hardships of frontier medical life. A few letters are addressed to "Dr." Jacob H. Clawson at the Ebenezer Academy near Rock Hill, S. C.
  - Cleburne, Patrick Ronayne papers, 1864
    This collection centers on a copy of a speech given by General Cleburne to the regimental commanders and general officers of the Army of the Tennessee on January 2, 1864. The copy was requested from Cleburne by General W. H. T. Walker to be forwarded to Jefferson Davis. Walker considered the address inflammatory and likely to result in "ruin" and "disgrace." The document itself, signed by Cleburne, is his famous suggestion that the Confederacy, by that time in dire circumstances, should free the slaves and muster them into the Army. Cleburne outlined the main reasons this would be beneficial: 1) the wind would be knocked out of Yankee moral zeal, 2) foreign countries would be morally free to give substantial aid to the South, 3) the actual size of the Army would be greatly augmented, and 4) the black population of the South would no longer constitute a threat as spies for the enemy.
  - Crawford, Samuel Wylie papers, 1861-1863
    Report to Lt. Col. F. T. Locke of the operations of the 3rd Division in the battles near Gettysburg [1863], a letter from John Titcomb Sprague, 1861, commenting on Fort Sumter and its commander, Robert Anderson; orders from Crawford, 1870, as commander of the United States troops in Alabama instructing officers on the policing of the polls during the coming election; and a letter from the sheriff of Montgomery, 1870, concerning the threat of a riot.
  - Davis, James M. papers, 1864
    Two letters written by Davis to his wife in Camden, South Carolina, during the Civil War. He wrote the week of May 7-10, 1864, of his efforts to rejoin his command.
  - Davis, Jefferson papers, 1841-1938
    Four items collected by the Daltons were combined with other Davis materials.
  - Deblois, Thomas A. papers, 1833
    Letter from Nathan Hale, editor of the Boston Daily Advertiser, to Deblois writing in support of Daniel Webster as a possible presidential candidate. Hale makes reference to Andrew Jackson and asks Dublois to pass an article about Webster on to Major Jack Downing (pseudonym for Seba Smith) for possible publication in the Portland Courier.
  - De la Rame´, Louise papers, circa 1893
    This signed manuscript is a translation of Louis-Adrien Levat's "La Disparition des Oiseaux" (La Nouvelle Revue, Vol. 80, Jan.-Feb. 1893, pp. 598-602). De la Rame´ was a translator of French who went by the pseudonym Ouida.
  - De Saussure Family papers, 1788-1916
    Correspondence and papers of Henry William De Saussure and of grandson Wilmot Gibbes De Saussure, South Carolina legislator and Confederate Army officer. Subjects include the establishment of South Carolina College (later the University of South Carolina), the Mexican War, conditions in the Confederacy, political phases of Reconstruction, an interview between Carl Schurz and Henry A. De Saussure, effect of the contested election of 1877, and the Charleston earthquake of August 31, 1886. Also included are documents concerning real estate transfers, and genealogical records of the Bacot, Burden, De Saussure, Gourdin, Hamilton, Mood, Pringle, and Swinton families. Among the correspondents and persons mentioned are P.G.T. Beauregard, Henry Alexander De Saussure, John M. De Saussure, Adam T. Millican, Benjamin Silliman, and Henry D.A. Ward. The 5 items collected by the Daltons were merged into this collection.
  - District of Columbia, Miscellany papers, 1815-1928
    These 22 items are largely correspondence written in Washington, DC or sent to Washington, DC. Examples include a 1928 letter from Herbert Hoover to John Mullowney of Nashville, TN, a 1901 letter from Senator Orville H. Platt to Julius Brown, Esq., an 1884 letter from Secretary of the Interior, Henry M. Teller to U. S. Representative Richard Warner, an 1881 letter from Supreme Court Justice John Marshall Harlan, an 1879 letter from then-U. S. Representative James A. Garfield to Joseph Carter of Missouri, an 1877 letter from Z. Chandler, Chairman of the National Republican Committee to George Carter of New Orleans, an 1863 and an 1866 letter from U. S. Representative Schuyler Colfax, and an 1865 letter written by Confederate veteran, George C. Watkins of Little Rock to Washington lawyer James Carlisle, regarding Watkins' legal post-war woes. This folder is in Box 3 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Dugas Family papers, 1763-1848
    Papers in this collection include letters, as well as financial and legal documents. The oldest item is a French marriage contract drawn in 1763, in the name of Louis Renee Adrien Dugas. Most of the material in the collection, however, pertains to Leon Frederick E. Dugas, who traveled extensively as a cotton merchant and general factor. Letters to Dugas discuss business and prices, as well as numerous lawsuits and disputes with importers. Several letters to Dugas from his brother-in-law and partner Paul Ronignol, are in French. A letterpress volume from 1845 records much of Dugas's correspondence from that year. Many of these letters are in French, and virtually all deal with matters of finance, cotton sales, or estate settlements. Of interest are documents representing Dugas's attempts to gain control of the Habersham Iron Works; papers relating to the sale of slaves to the family; and an inventory showing that in 1827, the Dugas family purchased most of the land, goods, and slaves of Good-Rest, the Edgefield, S.C. home of Dr. Beauregard.
- E-G
  - Ellet, William papers, 1761
    Book of arithmetic problems and rules.
  - Espy, James Pollard papers, 1844
    Collection centers on the rain theories of Espy. Included is the text of an address on artificial rain-making. There are also two documents from the citizens of Coudersport, Pennsylvania, who tried Espy's theories on a small scale and believed them to be effective.
  - Faunce, S.E. papers, 1861-1865
    Collection consists of a highly readable account of a Union soldier's experiences in the Civil War. It is in the form of a 48-page, typewritten memoir. There is no substantial clue to the identity of the author, but an attached business card is that of an "S.E. Faunce." The memoir describes events surrounding the 13th Mass. Volunteer Infantry, including the author's witnessing of the battle of Hampton Roads between the MONITOR and the MERRIMAC. Some relationship probably exists between the author of this memoir and Daniel W. Faunce, also of Plymouth.
  - Feaster Family papers, 1755-1860
    Collection contains mainly legal items, such as deeds and land grants. The evolution of a tract of land in S.C., 1755, may be traced to the Civil War.
  - Fludd, Eliza papers, 1865-1868
    Collection contains letters from Fludd mostly written to her friend, Mrs. Jolliffe. Fludd was the sister-in-law of a brother of George A. Trenholm, Secretary of the Treasury of the Confederate States of America. In clear handwriting, Fludd reveals herself to be deeply religious, well-educated, and a witness to the political and social events of the time; her context is Calvinist doctrine. She witnessed the battle and surrender of Fort Sumter and her belongings were destroyed or stolen when Sherman's army passed through Charleston. The letters describe her experiences and trials during the end of the Civil War. She gives an account of her radical change in lifestyle from living with abundance to starvation during Reconstruction, and also of the attitudes of the South to the North.
  - Frost, Arthur Burdett papers, 1913-1914
    Collection consists of two letters. One is from Katherine Hinton Wootten, librarian of the Carnegie Library in Atlanta, to Frost thanking him for his letter and drawing of Brer Rabbit. His reply from Switzerland gives news of his illness.
  - Gaffney Family papers, 1862-1866
    Letters to the Gaffney family of Columbia, S.C., from friends and relatives. A letter (1862) written by P. Lemmons of the 12th South Carolina infantry (Gregg's Brigade) while he was at Camp Arsenal Green in Charleston, S.C., describes the stealing of a steamship, THE PLANTER, by a party of African Americans. Several letters were written by William W. Gaffney to his parents during the Civil War: one (1862 May 20) from Camp Jackson in Spottsylvania, Va., These describe the events of battles in Virginia and Pennsylvania. Two items deal with financial matters at Furman University.
  - Gales & Seaton records, 1811-1868
    Collection contains the business papers of Joseph Gales, Jr., and William W. Seaton, editors of the National Intelligencer. Correspondence pertains to subscriptions, advertising, announcements and letters to the editors. Some prominent names appear in the subscription correspondence. Of particular interest are fifty-six transcripts of Congressional speeches, resolutions, and motions. These were presented for publication and are marked for editing. Among the authors of the manuscripts are Henry Clay, James K. Polk, Martin Van Buren, and Daniel Webster. Many are signed. Part of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Gaston, William papers, 1814, 1817
    Two letters written by Gaston [of New Bern, NC] to an unknown person. These letters are located in Box 4 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Georgia, Miscellany papers, 1806-1865
    Twelve items, miscellaneous in relation to one another, but all relate to Georgia. Items include a pledge of allegiance to the Union, signed by Andrew Young in 1865 and an 1806 pardon for Jedediah Seymore signed by Secretary of State Horatio Marbury. These items are located in Box 4 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Greenaway, Kate papers, 1895-1901
    Contains two letters written to a friend she addresses as Lady Maria. In the first letter she is trying to arrange a time for Lady Maria to visit her, and refers to Mr. Ponsonby, presumably Lady Maria's husband. In the second letter she thanks Lady Maria for flowers she has sent from Ireland; says she has influenza; and reports a coming art exhibit that would feature paintings by Sir John Everett Millais.
  - Great Britain, Miscellany papers, 1804-1939
    Primarily correspondence of various government departments and individuals.
- H-K
  - Hill, Daniel Harvey papers, 1923
    Two letters to Hill from the Adjutant General of the State of North Carolina regarding the service of North Carolinians in World War I. They are located in Box 4 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Huddleston, Eliza A. papers, 1861-1864
    Consists of Civil War correspondence between R. R. Huddleston, 6th Regiment of the S.C. Volunteers, and his wife, Eliza A. (Chandler) Huddleston. The first two letters, headed "York District, S.C.," are love letters written before the couple married in 1861. Soon after this, R. R. left for the war. His letters during the period 1862-1864 are from various places in Va., and contain occasional comments on battles and camp life. In one letter (Sept. 12, 1863) Huddleston recounts to his wife the story of having to watch as two fellow South Carolinians were shot for desertion.
  - Iredell, James papers, 1831-1842
    Three letters by Iredell addressed to John Branch, Secretary of the Navy; Gales and Seaton; and Willie P. Magnum and William A. Graham. The letter to branch recommends James H. Popelston for a midshipman's warrant. The letter to Gales and Seaton pertains to a subscription to the NATIONAL INTELLIGENCER. To Magnum and Graham, Iredell writes in support of James H. Brazier for appointment as midshipman, and requests that they forward his letter to Secretary of the Navy, Abel P. Upshur. On the same page, Magnum and Graham write a note of transmittal to Upshur, stating that they concur heartily with Iredell's recommendation.
  - Jackson, Andrew papers, 1820-1836